I think the most interesting question about Cedric Price would be something about
how he still, how is Cedric still a part of architectural culture today, in your
mind. That would be a possible question.
and in my view Cedric is a kind of figure that haunts architecture in its
contemporary life.
Cedric imagined architecture in the 21st century being something I think
fundamentally different
than what it's become. I think his career, his principles, his instinct was to see
architecture
as a culture of ideas and almost at times thought experiments about what the world
could be and
and that part of architecture's job was to ask questions about the world we know.
I think in that way he haunts architecture and what it's become
because of architecture's increasing and rampant professionalization,
commercial reality, and what I at times call almost industrial condition today.
Architecture is industrializing in at times what I would say are almost horrific
ways.
It's getting better at doing more and thinking less.
In other words, architecture is becoming less like Cedric than most of us could have
ever imagined.
My immediate impression, which I'll hold on to forever, is that he was an
Englishman.
And it had two distinct properties, let's say, for a crude American like me.
like me. One is Cedric's immediate wit and playfulness, which I think people have
too
often emphasized as the primary quality of his personality. He was a very witty guy.
On the surface, appeared to be very jokey and playful, but of course what he was
doing
with the kind of jokes he would make and the experiments and games that he would
play is
really interrogate the habits and the assumptions of architects. It was actually
deadly, deadly
serious work, but presented in the most English, low-key English of manners, I
think. Incredibly
brilliant kind of critical method. The playfulness was probably the most distinctive
property,
but the one is, at least as I got to know the body of work, which to this day I
still
think about. The flip side of that, Englishness, is in fact a deeply London
sensibility, which
is to see architecture in its global culture and to know exactly where modern
architecture
is at any one time in his life. And I don't know where that ability came from, but I
think
a huge part of that ability resulted from him being at a place that was deeply
connected
to what architecture was doing at all times. London, remember, is an incredibly
unique
architectural culture. It's very worldly and has been for decades. One of my
absolute favorite
pictures I have of events at the AA, which I've used in lectures around the world
forever,
This is a photograph taken in the late 1950s down in what now is our lecture hall,
and what at the time would have been a kind of member space for the association.
And in the middle of the long wall facing the square is an old,
and it looks to me like very grouchy Walter Gropius presenting a lecture
to the crowd of ladies and gentlemen at a series of dinner tables.
And it's a very beautiful picture, and Gropius has got his notes and his reading
glasses,
and he's making some pronouncement about what modern architecture is.
And in the foreground of that picture, sitting sort of sideways and looking down at
the floor,
is a young Cedric Price, who is the only person in the room not looking at Gropius.
And what Cedric is doing is sort of staring off into space and clearly processing
what Gropius is saying,
but in no way following the great master
in a way that every other person in that room is clearly doing.
Cedric is already, and this is only within a couple of years of his graduation,
thinking about architecture in different directions,
and I think it's quite an amazing kind of record of that capacity
from the very beginning of his career.
Again, I think the primary means for him to be able to do that
isn't just a kind of personal intelligence,
but a fact that he was being exposed to a range of ideas in modern architectural
culture here in the 1950s,
which is already a city that's globalizing and international in ways that few other
places were.
It's not unprecedented that some careers have influence because of activities other
than building.
Cedric is an extreme example of that.
I suppose the immediate answer many people would suggest
is that the ideas were of the kind of importance
that they gathered other minds around them that then did work
and we could then see influence being exerted
and that's a well-rehearsed genealogy
that I don't need to repeat here
Cedric's ideas become the basis for a kind of high-tech architecture
which is then commercialized, built by a generation
that comes after him
But I think the other reason that influence can be tracked in his career,
which I absolutely would subscribe to and believe in,
is because what we think of as influence is possible in that form
in that period of the 20th century especially,
i.e. at a moment when there wasn't a huge amount of building,
as things start to settle down after the rush of post-war building in England.
In fact, architectural culture during the 1960s and 70s
is really a world of not building.
I mean, terrifically so, you could say, almost.
That after the great boom of the 1950s,
when post-war England and much of Europe
has to rebuild itself after its destruction,
that activity begins to settle by the late 1950s
at exactly the moment Cedric's career starts to emerge.
And architecture becomes, you know,
and the AA is a tremendous record of this,
architecture becomes a discussion of ideas and principles
and possible projects, which of course we then see realized,
but only after economic and other activity starts to accelerate.
So, you know, Cedric's capacity to distill that possibility
happens at exactly the moment when that becomes a dominant mode
of transmitting what you and I would think of as influence.
The very opposite sort of condition is the case today, where basically everybody is
building,
and us trying to imagine how influence could be asserted by a set of principles or
ideas becomes nearly inconceivable.
In fact, it becomes a really interesting project again today,
and I think why us talking about Cedric would be so important, let's say, in 2014.
I think an interesting question is, what might be Cedric's most important project?
and my response would be his office,
the creating of his office
and not the specific designs
of any of his 160 design proposals.
If I'm right, the number is something like
150 or 160 projects he does
over the course of his four or five decades of work.
Everybody on the planet today
who loves the fun palace to death
wants to say there are some projects
that matter more than others.
I worry about a moment like ours where everybody can be so universally
agreed that Cedric's Fun Palace is the most important building of the
20th century. It just seems weird to me that we could all suddenly agree on that.
I tell you, I can go to juries all week long at the A and everybody will do nothing
but
endless praise on Fun Palace. I think that would terrify him as a kind of
generational condition.
I would, just to offer a slightly different view on that question,
and believe me, I love the Fun Palace for all the reasons everybody else does,
but I think actually the way he designs his office
becomes incredibly important
because he creates a model for an office that is a repository of ideas
much more than a factory for producing buildings.
And this I know because of the work that Samantha Hardingham
and other colleagues have done
on the archival organization of his office,
which he saw as one of his many design projects.
And of course what you can then realize looking back
is that Cedric understood all along the organization of knowledge,
even his own experience as an architect,
is something to be conscious of and articulate in his work as an architect.
Very, very few architects have that degree of self-awareness.
Most will see that as just the site where they do their serious work,
and the serious work will always be those buildings or proposals
or Cedric, for whatever reason,
had a level of self-consciousness and self-awareness
that allowed him to see that the creation
of that very special space of all architectural spaces,
which is the design studio,
needs to be brought on board as how you think about your career.
And he did that to an almost obsessive level
of cataloging and organizing and sorting drawings,
notes, sketches, postcards, newspaper clippings,
clippings into something that you and I would today think of as almost a kind of
curatorial
obsession. And I find that one of the least remarked upon qualities of his career,
which is
just, you know, the conversations we've had about the role of the archive today, an
incredibly
interesting model, let's say, for what architects might think about for the future.
I think it's an
interesting question how Cedric comes to an idea that he's often quoted for, which
is that an
architect is an enabler and not a builder. And what he points to is what by the
middle of the
20th century is a professional reality, which is that architects become largely
organizers and
managers of the flow of information and ideas around, for example, the building of
buildings,
but also many other activities. And it's been said by other people in the same years
that
Cedric is a part of the AA school, but that the
architect has a very unique position as a profession
of sitting in the center of all kinds of forms of expertise, and
he or she is the figure that has to manage that, that flow of information.
But the other thing he's doing, let's say, more
ideologically is saying, look, architecture is not equal to building.
Those two things are two very different worlds.
Buildings are important and they often play a role within architectural culture,
but architectural culture is really a world of ideas.
And ideas can be expressed and discovered and developed in many different forms
and not just actual building.
The making of drawings, the representing of how we move through space
and all of those kind of activities.
Rem once said that Price's intent was to make architecture indistinguishable from
the ordinary,
i.e. that architecture isn't separate from the everyday lives and spaces of the
city.
I think that's Rem's projection much more than Cedric's ambition.
I think that might be the case that Cedric wanted to live that way very much
and wanted to be very much indistinguishable from the wonderful world that he lived
in
and was a part of and much larger than architectural culture.
But that's a very different thing than trying to make the case that that's what
architecture should become.
In fact, I think one of Cedric's most interesting qualities
is that he shied away from the instinct
that Kuhlhaus and many others embodies today,
which is to see architecture as a set of large-scale principles
that apply across very wide audiences
and not just to individual careers.
I think part of the brilliance of Cedric's career
is that it was always thought of in very intimate and very personal terms.
In fact, almost in ways in which it would be very hard
for you and I to even apply some of what he does to our own lives.
Which is a very, very different model than you could say the kind of classical
modernism of Kuhlhaus' stance, which is to say, what I do
becomes a model for what architecture should become. Very interesting and
complex debate there, and that sort of thing. Maybe that's the one lesson of
Cedric's
that isn't often taken on board by his otherwise deeply
convinced followers of what he was arguing for.
It's an interesting question many people pose, which is what might possibly be
Cedric's relevance to architecture in our time.
And I would say to learn from it from a distance, to not try and embody that
project, to not try and extend it.
I think, for me, one of the most unnerving questions of Cedric's career now is how
and why does it live in the way that it does,
i.e. largely forgotten and literally buried in the cold ground below Montreal in the
CCA,
which I find at times shocking.
It's such an important body of work and is already now so distant from where
architecture is
that I think like many people, and I know you are in the making of a film like this,
our speculation on how to bring those ideas back
is in fact an incredibly important project.
I don't have an answer to how to do that now.
I think at a personal level, for example, as a publisher,
I couldn't be more happy than to have helped people like yourselves,
not just with this project, but with the brilliant work you guys did
a couple of years ago, gathering Cedric's writings together.
I think Samantha's two-volume definitive career monograph
on a hidden career that will come out at the end of this year
and will document 50 years of architectural discovery
will be the book of our time.
There will be no more important book in our time published.
Not just because it will be able to reveal the scope of a career
that very few people actually know,
other than through one or two images,
but also to see its true breadth from lectures, performances, installations,
to the design of buildings, to the making of an office,
to a teaching career, to his activities as a critic.
All of that will be important.
But those are just, I think, the beginnings of the ways
in which we really tease out the bigger questions,
which is how can one make careers like that
for a generation of architects emerging today alive again
and available for their reinvention and rediscovery
and appropriation and use.
And I think Cedric would always say misuse by those who come after.
I think the last thing he would want of us is that we worship him.
I think he went out of his way, in fact,
to make sure that would never happen.
And I think we have to remember he was doing that at a time
in which the architect as a kind of cult figure,
designer, celebrity, proprietary operating system
was emerging in the latter decades of the 20th century,
he did everything he could do
to make sure he would never be that kind of a figure.
Again, likely just instinct
and a very good, light, magic touch
in terms of how to live in the world properly.
But I think he's seen the horrors
of what architecture was becoming,
however brilliant its propositions were
in the early 20th century.
In the closing decades of the 20th century,
he's seen professional activity,
architectural education, architectural journalism,
all of these things literally industrializing
into big, large-scale commercial activities
that weren't really offering more and more ideas
for the world to speculate on and think about,
but just simply keeping themselves alive
as little self-sustaining things.
And I think what he really asks us all to do
is to stand back from that activity periodically
and to think again for the ways in which,
even at the most individual, personal level,
we can offer or speculate upon alternatives to that kind of reality.
And I think that's the one thing he would want us to do today
and we should all try and do for Cedric, if not for ourselves.